Louis I. Newman Papers
Louis I. Newman Papers
1926-1968
Newman, Louis Israel, 1893-
0.5 linear feet
Papers of the Rabbi, writer. Correspondence; manuscripts; and printed material including newsletters, a poem, sermons, and a book. Notable correspondents include Albert M. Bender and Nelson Glueck (president of Hebrew Union College).
149393
Biographical History
Louis I. Newman was an American rabbi, scholar and writer. Despite having no formal rabbinical training he was ordained in 1918 by Steven S. Wise, a Hungarian-born Reform rabbi and Zionist leader, and eventually became the rabbi for Congregation Rodeph Sholom in New York City. Newman was active in the Zionist movement, held a leadership position in United Palestine Appeal, and during World War II he campaigned in the United States for assistance and support in smuggling Jews from Europe to Palestine. He did not hesitate to use his pulpit to publish his strongly-held beliefs; in 1939 his condemnations from the pulpit of British policy toward Palestine led the Board of his synagogue to pressure him to resign from United Palestine Appeal.
Newman is the editor or author of several books, among them The Hasidic Anthology: Tales and Teachings of the Hasidim, The Talmudic anthology: Tales and Teachings of the Rabbis, A "Chief Rabbi" of Rome Becomes a Catholic (concerning Rabbi Israel Anton Zolli who was baptized a Christian in 1945), and a collection of sermons entitled Biting on Granite. He also wrote a number of pamphlets and booklets and at least one song, and his sermons have been published.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Louis I. Newman Papers is divided into three series. A good amount is related to Albert M. Bender, philanthropist, book collector, and patron of the arts; the material suggests that Newman was writing something about Bender.
Correspondence-subject files contains correspondence to, from, or about Albert M. Bender, and newsletters and President's Reports from Hebrew Union College. Printed material consists of programs and other items published by Newman's Congregation Rodeph Sholom and miscellaneous other printed material. Writings contains typescripts of articles and essays by Newman, research material and notes on Albert M. Bender, and a copy of Newman's book Hasidic Anthology.
Arrangement of the Collection
Folders are arranged alphabetically within series but material has not been arranged below the folder level and is in no particular order.
Separated Material
Rabbi Newman's papers originally included a number of published books which have been transferred to Rare Books for separate cataloging. Please refer to for a complete listing of these.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; Activism and social reform; Newman, Louis I. (Louis Israel), 1893-1972.; Bender, Albert M. (Albert Maurice), 1866-1941.; Glueck, Nelson, 1900-; Congregation Rodeph Sholom (New York, N.Y.); Hebrew Union College.; Hasidic anthology: tales of the Hasidim.; Jews -- United States.; Judaism -- Clergy.; Rabbis -- New York (State); Zionism.; Zionists -- New York (State); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Programs (documents); Sermons.; Sheet music.; Rabbis.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Louis I. Newman, 1968-1971.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Bender, Albert M., ca. 1926-1950 (Box 1)
  - Hebrew Union College, 1967-1968; newsletters and correspondence from Israel (from Nelson Glueck and others); 2 folders (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Congregation Rodeph Sholom, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1964; 1965 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Articles and essays, 1947; 1960?,; 1967; includes Newman's personal account of the U.N. Partition Decision of November 1939; some items may be sermons (Box 1)
  - Bender material, notes, fragments and drafts concerning Albert M. Bender (Box 1)
  - Book: The Hasidic Anthology, Schocken Books, 1963 (Box 1)